Guide to the John Cowper Powys Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
John Cowper Powys collection
1930-1963
GEN MSS 136
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.83
(2 boxes)
The collection consists of miscellaneous letters by John Cowper Powys.
Powys, John Cowper, 1872-1963
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This listing encompasses accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts pertaining to John Cowper Powys acquired by gift and purchase from various sources by the Beinecke Library. Materials acquired prior to January 1995 have been arranged in Series I, Letters, which consists of letters by John Cowper Powys and is alphabetically arranged by recipient. Materials acquired since January 1995 are located in Series II, Additions since January 1995, and are listed in accession order.
Authors, English -- 20th Century -- Archives; Playter, Phyllis; Powys, John Cowper, 1872-1963; Powys, Llewelyn, 1884-1939
- Letters, 1950 Oct 29; Series I
  - Letter: Corwen, Merionethshire, North Wales, to Ben Abramson, 1950 Oct 29 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    1 item (2 leaves); 20cm.
    ALS containing news of Alyse Gregory.
    With envelope.
    With: TLS from Ben Abramson to Norman
    [Holmes] Pearson, 1953 May 13.
    1 item (1 leaf); 26cm.
    "Sent to Rare Book Room 27 N[ov] 1961."
  - Letters: Corwen, Merionethshire, North Wales, to John Badham, 1944-47 (Box 1, Folder 2-7)
    17 items.
    15 ALS and 2 autograph postcards
    concerning Powys' health, work on Rabelais and Dostoievsky, and
    the birth of Badham's son.
    With: 15 envelopes.
    With: 3 autograph postcards, signed,
    by P[hyllis] Playter to John Badham,
    1945 Sep-Oct.
    Purchased in 1991.
  - Letters: Corwen, Merionethshire, North Wales, to George X. Basarab, 1943-59 (Box 1, Folder 8-12)
    15 items.
    14 ALS and 1 AL containing biographical
    information on Powys and Phyllis
    Playter and discussion of his literary
    tastes.
    ALS of 1947 Jun 3 includes pen-and-ink
    caricature of Playter reading Sartre
    to Powys.
    With: 14 envelopes (one letter on
    aerogram form).
    Purchased in 1995.
  - Letter: Blaenau-Ffestiniog, Merionethshire, North Wales, to Juanita [Berlin], 1957 May 15 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    1 item (2 leaves); 23 cm.
    ALS.
  - Letter: Blaenau-Ffestiniog, Merionethshire, North Wales, to Juanita [Berlin], 1957 May 29 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    1 item (1 leaf); 23 cm.
    With: envelope.
    Purchased in 1992.
  - Letters: Blaenau-Ffestiniog, Merionethshire, North Wales, to Laura Coster, 1959-62 (Box 1, Folder 15-27)
    64 items.
    64 ALS containing biographical and
    personal information about Powys
    and commentary on Sappho, the English
    Romantics, and other authors.
    With: 63 envelopes.
    Purchased in 1990.
  - Letters: Corwen, Merionethshire, North Wales, to Ormond Coulam, 1935-39 (Box 1, Folder 28-29)
    11 items.
    11 ALS discussing Powys' works,
    Coulam's 1936 visit to Wales and his
    subsequent marriage.
    With: 9 envelopes.
  - Letters: Merionethshire, North Wales, to Curtis Freshel, 1936-60 (Box 1, Folder 30-35)
    29 items.
    29 ALS discussing Powys' writings,
    views on European politics of the
    late 1930s, religious beliefs, and
    reading.
    Letter of 17 Jul 1952 in the hand of
    Phyllis Playter.
    With: 8 envelopes.
    Purchased in 1994.
  - Letter: 148 Waverly Place, New York City, to Mrs. Curtis Freshel, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 36)
    1 item (2 leaves); 22 cm.
    ALS to Mrs. Curtis Freshel concerning
    a lecture tour.
  - Letter: Corwen, Merionethshire, North Wales, to Mrs. G. M. Green, 1954 Nov 3 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    1 item (1 leaf); 20 cm.
  - Letter: Corwen, Merioneth[shire], North Wales, to Terence Greenidge, 1940 Feb 23 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    1 item (2 leaves); 21 cm.
    ALS concerning publication prospects
    of Owen Glendower.
  - Letters: Corwen, Merionethshire, North Wales, to Evelyn Hardy, 1950, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    2 items.
    2 ALS concerning Hardy's writing on
    Swift and Hardy.
    Purchased in 1964.
  - Postcard: Corwen, Merioneth[shire] to Huw? Menai, 1953 Oct 9 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    1 item (1 leaf); 14 cm.
    Autograph postcard signed.
  - Letter: Blaenau-Ffestiniog, Merionethshire, North Wales, to F. G. Walker, 1955 May 6 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    ALS concerning Llewellyn Powys.
  - Letters: Blaenau-Ffestiniog, Merionethshire, North Wales, to Lily M. Walsh, 1957, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    2 ALS containing biographical
    information.
    With: 2 envelopes.
    With: 2 ALS from Phyllis Playter to
    Lily Walsh concerning the last
    illness and death of Powys. Both
    with envelopes, 1962, 1963.
  - Letter: Corwen, Merionethshire, North Wales, to Richard Heron Ward, 1945 Jan 30 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    ALS containing news of Powys and
    his associates.
    Purchased in 1993.
  - Letter: Corwen, Merioneth[shire], North Wales, to Richard Heron Ward, 1954 Mar 5 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    1 item (1 leaf); 21 cm.
  - Letter: Blaenau-Ffestiniog, Merionethshire, North Wales to [John Foster White?], 1958 Jul 13 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    With: envelope addressed to "Miss
    L. M. Walsh," postmarked 1958 Jun 15.
    With: TL (carbon) from Phyllis Playter
    to John Foster White, concerning the
    death of Powys, 1963 Jul 3.
  - Letter: Corwen, Merioneth[shire], North Wales, to "Francis", 1951 Dec 18 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    1 item (1 leaf); 20cm.
    AL.
  - Letter: Corwen, Merioneth[shire], North Wales, to "My dear and most gallant and generous friend", 1950 May 26 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    1 item (4 leaves); 20cm.
    AL (possibly incomplete).
  - Letter: Corwen, N[orth] Wales, to "My dear friend", 1950 Oct 9 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    ALS discussing the writing of Henry
    Miller.
  - Letter: Corwen, Merioneth[shire], North Wales, to "my dearest Nephew", 1951 Dec 13 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Letter: Corwen, Merionethshire, North Wales, to "my dear friend", 1953 Oct 21 (Box 2, Folder 50)
- Additions Since January 1995, Series II
  - HOUGHTON, CLAUDE, 1889-
    - Letters to John Cowper Powys: Savage Club, London, 1958-60 (Box 2, Folder 51)
      6 items.
      6 ALS discussing personal news,
      friends and family members, and
      authors including Henry Miller,
      James Hanley and Theodore Powys.
      Letter of 10 Oct 1960 mentions an
      enclosed sonnet (not present).
      With: 6 envelopes. (One envelope,
      postmarked 23 Dec 1959, not
      accompanied by a letter.)
  - POWYS, JOHN COWPER, 1872-1963
    - Letters to Nettie Packer: Corwen, Merionethshire, North Wales, 1944-48 (Box 2, Folder 52)
      libraries and their users, London
      during World War II, and authors
      including Edgar Allan Poe and
      Aristophanes.
      With: a pen and ink sketch map of
      Corwen and the route to Powys's
      house.
      With: 6 envelopes.
      Purchased in 1996.
    - Letters to Peter Wiener: Corwen, Merionethshire, North Wales, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 53)
      2 brief ALS commenting on Wiener's
      arrival with his collection and
      an introduction to Powys's cousin
      Trevor Moillet.
    - Letters to Bill Bax: Corwen, Merionethshire, North Wales, 1938-45, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 54-56)
      25 items.
      25 ALS discussing personal news,
      friends and family members, World
      War II and fascism, Powys' writings,
      and authors including Homer,
      Sophocles, George Borrow, and
      Henry James.
      With: 3 incomplete letters from
      Powys to Bax and 1 ALS from Phyllis
      Playter to Bax.
    - Letter: Corwen, Merionethshire, North Wales, to M. J. Dewar, 1938 Jul 29 (Box 2, Folder 57)
      1 item (2 leaves); 20 cm.
      ALS in response to an autograph
      request.
      Purchased in 1997.
    - Letters to Mrs. Robert Mantner: Corwen, Merionethshire, North Wales, 1946, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 58)
      2 ALS concerning Powys' health
      and daily events.
      With envelopes.
    - Letters: Blaenau-Ffestiniog, Merionethshire, North Wales, to Mr. Disspain, 1956, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 59)
      2 ALS concerning Disspain's request
      for an autograph.
    - Letters: Blaenau-Ffestiniog, Merionethshire, North Wales, to Reid Crowell, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 60)
      5 items.
      5 ALS discussing Crowell's poetry
      and that of his mother, Grace Noll
      Crowell.
      With: ALS from Powys to Grace Noll
      Crowell, 1958 Sep 12, and 3
      typescript carbons of letters from
      Reid Crowell to Powys.
    - Letter: Corwen, Merionethshire, North Wales, to Sheridan Van Dolan, 1954 Dec 15 (Box 2, Folder 61)
      1 item (2 l.); 20 cm.
      ALS praising Van Dolan's poetry
      and discussing other authors.
    - Letters: to Mrs. Esther MacMillan, 1950-59 (Box 2, Folder 62-66)
      5 ALS concerning her search for
      several of his books and daily
      news.
      With: TLS to Macmillan from Bertram
      Rota, Ltd., 1950 May 18; and ALS
      to Macmillan from Francis Powys,
      1952 Jan 18.
    - Letter: 439 W. 21 [Street], N.Y., to Mr. Davenport, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 67)
      1 item (2 L.); 21 cm.
      ALS thanking him for an invitation
      to the theater but sending regrets.
      Purchased in 1998.
    - Letters: Blaenau-Ffestiniog, Merionethshire, North Wales, to Sven Berlin, 1957 Oct, Dec (Box 2, Folder 68)
      2 ALS, one containing reminiscences
      of the Powys' brothers lives and
      friends in New York City.
    - Letter: Blaenau-Ffestiniog, Merionethshire, North Wales, to Mr. W. Disspain, 1959 Jun 4 (Box 2, Folder 69)
      1 item (1 L.); 21 cm.
      ALS concerning reading and the history of Guy Fawkes night. Purchased in 1998.
    - Letters: to Eleanor Johnson, 1930-58 (Box 2, Folder 70-71)
      10 items.
      7 ALS discussing reading,
      books by the Powys brothers
      and family matters.
      Accompanied by: TLS to Johnson
      from G. Arnold Shaw, 1936
      Feb 9, concerning her collecting
      of Powys first editions; ALS
      to Johnson from "Hattie," n.d.,
      concerning a debate between Powys
      and Bertrand Russell on "Is Marriage
      a Failure?" and ALS to Johnson from
      "Pat,"1937 Jan 25.
      With: envelopes.
      Purchased in 2001.
      Acc #: 20010309-p
  - POWYS, THEODORE FRANCIS, 1875-1953
    - "The Key of the Field": AMS, [1926] (Box 2, Folder 72)
      1 v.; 23 cm.
      Notebook containing fair copy
      of short story on 36 numbered
      pages (rectos only).
      Signature at end.
      Binding: cloth backed marbled
      boards.
      Acc #: 20010724-b
    - "The Dewpond": AMS, [1926] (Box 2, Folder 73)
      1 item; 26 cm.
      Exercise book containing manuscript,
      corrected and signed, of short story
      on 31 numbered pages (rectos only).
      Binding: gray paper wrapper.
      With: ALS and envelope to Douglas
      Clayton concerning "The Dewpond,"
      1929 Sep 12.
      Acc #: 20010724-c
  - POWYS, JOHN COWPER, 1872-1963
    - Letter: 7 Cae Coed, Corwen, Merionethshire, North Wales, to George Moor, 1951 Nov 16 (Box 2, Folder 74)
      1 item; 20 cm.
      ALS saying that he has enjoyed
      reading Moor's masque, "The
      Trial of the Jewelled Peacock"
      and hopes it will be performed.
      Acc #: 20020812-j
    - Letter: 7 Cae Coed, Corwen, Merionethshire, North Wales, to "Paulette, John and Michael", 1954 Dec 24 (Box 2, Folder 75)
      ALS thanking them for Christmas
      wishes.
      Purchased in 2002.
      Acc.: 20020812-k
    - Letter: 7 Cae Coed, Corwen, Merionethshire, North Wales, to "My dear Lady", 1954 Apr 16 (Box 2, Folder 76)
      ALS thanking her for sending him
      Huxley's The Art of Seeing. Purchased in 2003.
      Acc.: 20030114-r